好的。
Alright.
大家早上好，下午好，
Good morning or good afternoon everyone,
我要开始了，
I'm like to get started,
大家能听到我说话吗？
can people hear me?
是的。
Yep.
谢谢。
Thank you.
好的，今天我想做的是
Alright, today, what I'd like to do is
给你们一个机会询问关于 xv6 的问题，
give you a chance to ask questions about xv6
以及最近的实验，
and about the recent labs,
为了给我们提供一些可以谈论的东西，
in order to give us something to talk about,
我会尽可能多地做写入时复制 fork 实验，
I'm going to do as much as I can of the copy-on-write fork lab here,
给我们一些可以考虑的东西，
just to give us something to chew on
你可以随意问任何问题，
and you should feel free to ask any questions you like,
你可以问为什么我的解决方案与你的不同，
you can ask about why my solution is different from your solution
或者为什么 xv6 这样工作，
or why xv6 works the way it does
为什么我们遇到的 bug 以这种方式出现。
or why the bugs that we encounter show up in the way they do.
所以只想提醒一下，
So just to remind you,
虽然我相信不需要提醒你们，
although I'm sure this is I'm sure I don't need to remind you,
写入时复制 fork 的关键点是
the point of copy-on-write fork is
为了避免在 fork 时对未修改页面的复制成本。
to avoid copying costs for pages at fork that are never modified.
我输入了几行代码，
I put in a few lines of code
来测量 memcpy 必须复制的字节数的减少，
to measure the reduction in the number of bytes that memcpy had to copy
对于我的写入时复制解决方案在 usertests 时，
during usertests for my copy-on-write solution
结果发现实际上减少了 90% 的复制量。
and found that actually reduce the amount of copying by 90%.
这是针对 usertests 的，
And this is for usertests
虽然是一个有点怪异的程序，但无所谓，
which is kind of a weird program, but nevertheless,
我认为这很大程度上是因为指令页的复制减少了，
and I think a lot of it is reductions in's copy of the instruction pages,
因为指令页从来不会修改，
because the instruction pages for are never modified,
所以不需要复制它们，
so there's never any point in having copies of them
我认为这就是很多优势的来源。
and I think that's where a lot of the win was from.
并且写入时复制 fork 还减少了 RAM 的使用，
And copy-on-write fork also reduces RAM use,
你需要使用的最大 RAM 量，
the sort of maximum amount of RAM you ever need to use
它减少了你花在 fork 上的时间，
and it reduces the amount of time you spend in fork,
所以 fork 返回得更快。
and so fork returns more quickly.
从另一方面来说，当然总成本可能会更高，
You know on the other hand, of course the total cost may be larger,
因为如果程序最终修改了所有写入时复制页面，
because if programs end up modifying all the copy-on-write pages,
你不得不做所有的复制，再加上所有的页面错误，
you end up having to do all the copies plus take all the page faults,
这可能有点昂贵，
which can be a little bit expensive,
但尽管如此，人们发现，一般说来，这是一种净收益。
but nevertheless, people found that, in general, it's a net benefit.
如你所知，主要的挑战是，
And as you know the main challenges are,
一个挑战是如何避免释放内存，
one challenge is how to avoid freeing memory
现在我们在进程之间共享页面，
and now we're sharing pages among processes,
没有释放它们，
have not de-allocate them, have not free them,
直到最后一个进程完成使用它们。
until the last process is finished using them,
所以任何[]。
so anymore bookkeeping.
另一个有趣的挑战是，
And the other interesting challenge is
特别是 xv6 中的 copyout ，
that there's a in copyout in particular the xv6,
修改用户内存，而无需实际使用 MMU 分页硬件，
modifies user memory without actually going to the MMU paging hardware,
我们必须在这里模仿页面错误。
and we have to mimic page faults here.
我要看实验了，
I'm gonna go to the lab,
从写入时复制实验的开头开始，
starting at the beginning the copy-on-write lab,
在我开始之前，
before I start,
我想提一下，
I just wanna just mentioned
我在做实验时遵循的策略，
the strategy that I think of myself as following when I do labs
我做了很多实验，一年又一年，
and I do a lot of labs from one year to the next,
我不记得做实验的细节了，
I don't remember the details of how to do the labs,
另外，实验也发生了变化。
and in addition labs change.
好的，当我做实验的时候，
Alright, so, when I'm doing the labs,
我总是迈出一小步，
I always take small steps,
我可能会发现要解决的问题的下一个子集，
I may find you know some sort of next subset of the problem to solve,
可能有五到十行代码，
maybe five or ten lines of code,
我编写程序并运行它，然后试着让它工作，
I programmed up and run it and try to get to working,
在我继续下一步之前，
before I go on to the next, proceeding to the next step
这是，而不是整体思考并编写一个完整的解决方案，
and this is you know as opposed to for example thinking through and writing a complete solution,
在开始测试和调试之前，
before starting to test and debug,
它总是一次测试和调试一点，
it always test and debug a little bit at a time,
这很大程度上是因为，
a lot of the reason for that is that,
即使你可能对很多事情都有一些想法，
even though you may, you may have sort of thought through a lot of things,
很多挑战，
a lot of the challenges,
还有很多设计，
and a lot of the design,
你要做什么才能解决实验的问题，
for what you're going to have to do to solve the lab,
我发现至少经常会有惊喜。
I find at least there's often surprises.
所以如果我先实现所有的东西，
And so if I implement everything first,
我可能会发现我浪费了很多时间，
I may find then that I've wasted a lot of time,
因为我没有完全理解这个问题，
because I didn't fully understand the problem,
直到我真正开始调试它。
until I actually got into debugging it.
我在每个点上选择下一步的方式是
And the way I choose the next step at each point is
通常是由测试失败引起的 panic 或崩溃引起的，
usually driven by whatever panic or crash a test failure I see that,
告诉我下一步需要解决的问题。
sort of tells me what I need to fix next.
我在做这个实验，
Well I'm doing this lab,
我会犯几个错误，
I'll make a few mistakes,
这是我上一次做实验时做的，
that I actually made the last time I did the lab,
我们可以一起做一个小的调试练习。
so that we can do a have a little practice debugging together.
再说一遍，你可以随时打断，问任何问题。
Again, feel free to break in at any time and ask questions about anything.
我从写入时复制实验的最新拷贝开始，
I'm starting here with fresh copy of the copy-on-write lab,
和你们所有人一样的源码。
source the same as all of you did.
所以，我要开始了。
So, I'll just fire this up.
并且，运行写入时复制测试，
And, run the copy-on-write tests
也许我很幸运，
and you know maybe I'll get lucky
所有测试都会通过，不需要做任何事，
and all the tests will pass and don't have to do anything,
不好，测试失败了，
too bad, on the test failed,
好的，不用太惊讶。
okay, so not too surprising.
这时好的步骤就是
And you know a good step at this point is
去看看测试，
to go have a look at the tests
弄清楚它想要做什么，
and figure out what it's trying to do,
令人难受的是，有些测试很复杂，很难理解，
and the sad truth is some of the tests are complicated and hard to understand
不一定是测试任何特定的东西，
and don't necessarily test anything specific,
它们只是尝试不同的东西，看看会不会断掉，
they just sort of try different things, see if something will break,
但幸运的是，这个简单的测试，
but luckily with this simple test,
它的作用非常清楚。
it's pretty clear what its doing.
一个问题。
A question.
嗯。
Yeah.
你需要显示一下你的屏幕，我们什么也看不见。
You need to show your screen, we cannot see anything.
哦，天哪。
Oh gosh.
不好意思,
I'm sorry about that,
谢谢你让我知道。
thank you for, thank you for letting me know.
这好了吗？
How is that better?
是的。
Yes.
太棒了，好的。
Brilliant, alright.
好的，这是第一个 bug 。
Okay, well, that's bug number one.
好的，我在这里，
Okay, so I'll just, here I am,
在我的写入时复制测试中，
in my copy-on-write test,
我运行了写入时复制测试，但是失败了。
I ran copy-on-write test, and it fails.
看看这个测试，
Look at the test,
屏幕右边的 simpletest 失败了，
this simpletest on the screen right is actually failed,
这个测试，我们很幸运，它告诉我们它在做什么，
and this test, we're lucky enough, it actually tells us what it's doing
分配 xv6 中超过一半的可用内存，然后 fork ，
and allocates what it knows to be more than half the available memory in xv6 and then forks
当然，这个失败的原因是 fork 复制了一份，
and of course, the reason this fails is that fork makes a copy,
然后 xv6 从字面上复制了，
then ordinary xv6 actually literally makes a copy
所以，如果我们必须复制一半以上的内存，
and so if we have to copy more than half of memory,
就会没有足够的空间。
there's just not enough space for that.
好的，所以，这就是写入时复制的意义所在，
Okay, so, of course, this is what copy-on-write all about,
我们知道游戏是不用复制进程的内存，
and we know that the basic game is that instead of copying the process's memory,
我们只复制它的页表，而不是内存，
we want to just copy its page table and not the memory,
子进程只有一份父进程页表的复制，而不是内存，
the child just has a carbon copy of the parent's page table, instead of memory,
指向所有相同的物理页面。
referring to all the same physical pages.
fork 执行复制的位置在 vm.c 和 uvmcopy 中。
The place where, fork does it's copying is in vm.c and uvmcopy.
所以我们只需修改这个代码，
And so we can just modify this code,
以代替分配页面内存，
to instead of allocating a page memory,
在这里，并复制到上面，
here, and copying onto it,
我们要去掉这三行。
we're going to eliminate those three lines,
取而代之的是，
and instead,
我只是复制页表条目，
I just copied page table entries,
所以，
so um,
实际上就是想 hack 这个 mappages 的复制，
actually just gonna hack, this copy of mappages,
因为我们没有在这里分配内存，
since we didn't actually allocate memory here,
我要把删掉这个 free ，
going to get rid of this free,
我将修复这个 mappages ，
I'm going to fix this mappages,
而不是将 mem 映射到地址 i ，
to instead of mapping mem at address i,
我要映射 pa ，
I'm going to map the pa,
它是我们从父进程页表中取出的物理地址。
which is the physical address, we pulled out of the parents' page table.
这里能明白吗？
So is that clear?
所以这会产生这样的效果
And so this will just have the effect of
将所有父页面映射到子页面的地址空间。
mapping all of the parents pages into the child's address space.
pa 不是已经是 uint64 了吗？
Isn't pa already uint64?
可能吧。
Probably.
或者，如果你强制转换为已经是的类型，是不是很糟糕？
Or is it is it bad, if you were to cast its already that type?
强制转换什么也没做，除了让编译器闭嘴，
The cast does absolutely nothing other than shut the compiler up,
因为地址已经是 64 位，
since it's already, since addresses already 64 bits
你想要 64 位，
and you want 64 64 bit,
那个强制转换不会改变位，
that cast doesn't change the bits,
它只是让类型检查器不那么烦躁，
it just makes the type checker less upset,
但是[]你并不知道是哪一种类型。
but [] you actually don't know whether any of these types are.
但是，有一件事是我们不需要这个 mem 变量。
However, one thing is we don't need this mem variable.
好的，那么你写下 pa ，
Okay, so you write about pa,
天哪，我在想我们是不是完成了。
gosh, I wonder if we're done now.
我们来运行 cowtest ，看看会发生什么，
Let's run the cowtest and see what happens,
绝对没完成。
definitely not done.
好的，我们在这里有，
Okay, so, we got here is,
这个 usertrap 和 scause 2 。
this usertrap with scause of two.
有人记得 scause 2 是什么吗？
Anybody remember what scause two is?
我就直接告诉你吧。
I'll just tell you.
指令失效？
Instruction failure?
这是非法指令，
It's an illegal instruction,
那么我们为什么会得到非法指令。
so why would we getting an illegal instruction now.
这是我们所期待的吗？
Is this what we expected?
我们有没有覆盖有指令的位置？
Did we overwrite them like position where we have instructions?
是的，有些东西破坏了用户程序的指令。
Yes, something is damaging the instructions of the user program.
当然，我们在这里得到错误并不奇怪。
And of course the fault, we're not surprised we get a fault here.
但我们希望是保存的错误，
But we're hoping for write, for stored faults
驱动复制进程和写入时复制。
to drive the copying process and copy-on-write.
我们没有得到保存的错误。
We're not getting the store fault.
对此还有其他假设吗？
Any other hypotheses for this?
It's not really fair,
因为这是我的 bug ，不是你的 bug ，
because like this, my bug not your bug,
但是不管怎样。
but nevertheless.
一定要操作 flags 吗？
Does it have to do the flags?
是的，确实如此。
Yes, it does.
好的，那我把它放在一边，
Okay, so I'll just leave that to the side,
它们会再次出现。
they'll actually come up again.
另一个问题是我们希望出现保存页面错误，
Another question is we're hoping for store page faults,
这将驱动复制进程。
which will drive the copying process.
为什么我们没有得到保存页面错误？
Why didn't we get a store page fault?
好的，嗯。
Alright, um.
为什么我们会得到保存页面错误？
Why would we get a store page fault?
RISC-V 在什么情况下会产生保存页面错误。
Under what circumstances, does the RISC-V generate store page fault.
如果没有设置写标志，我们会得到，
We would get if the write flag is not set,
但现在我们可以正常地写任何东西。
but now we can just write to everything normally.
是的，设置写标志，
Yeah, left the write flag set,
好的，这就是第一个 bug ，
alright, so that's bug one
我上一次做这个实验的时候，
which I did actually make last time I did this lab,
所以，我在父级中设置了写标志，
so I've left the write flag set in the parent,
我没有对写标志做任何事情，
I've done I haven't done anything to the write flags,
这里的标志变量是，
this flags variable here is,
就是我们从父页表获得的，
it's just the way we pulled out of the parents' page table,
它的所有页面都是可写的，
it's all its pages are writable
所以这意味着它在子页表也可写，
and so that means that it's going to be writable on the child two,
我们不会得到保存页面错误，
we won't get store page faults,
所以只是共享一个页面可读写，
so just sharing a page read, write,
这不是我们想要的，
which is not what we wanted,
那我怎么才能关掉，
so how am I going to turn off the,
我该如何写保护这些页面。
how am I gonna write protect these pages.
有什么建议吗，我应该输入什么。
Any proposals, what should I type.
怎么样。
How about.
你可以使用 flags &= ~PTE_W 。
You can do flags and equals the wave sign underscore W.
是的，我们需要一个波浪号，
Yeah, yeah we're gonna need a tilde there,
我把那个波浪标志叫做波浪号，
I call that wave sign tilde,
我们需要波浪号，
the we need to the waves,
我们需要清除 flags 上的这一位，
the it's clear we need to clear this bit on the flags,
我们将保留所有其他 flags 的设置。
we're going to leave all the other flags set.
好的，这样清除了父页表还是子页表的标志？
Okay, so that's gonna with this clear the flag of the parent or the child?
子页表？
Child?
只是子页表。
Just child.
那么我如何清除，
So how do I clear,
我需要清除父页表中的标志吗？
do I also need to clear the flag in the parent?
是的，因为我们希望子页表独立于父页表，
Yes, because we want the child to be independent to the parents,
如果我们写了一些东西，
if we write something,
我们不想让子页表也得到父页表的修改。
we don't want the child to also get them modification from their parents.
完全正确，
That's absolutely right,
我们也需要对父页表进行写保护，
we need to write protect the page at the parent as well,
因为我们不想让子页表看到父页表的修改，
because we don't want the child to see the parents modifications,
所以试图模仿完全不同的副本。
so trying to mimic, having completely separate copies.
那么我能怎么来清除父页表中的标志呢？
So what can I do to clear the flag in the parents' page table?
你可以使用 *pte &= ~PTE ，对吧。
You can do something like star pte and equals not pte, right.
是的，我有父页表的，
Yeah, so I have the parents p-,
一个指向父页表条目的指针，就在 pte 中，
a pointer to the parents' page table entry right here in pte
所以我可以这里清除 PTE 标志，
and so I can clear the PTE flag here too,
这是很方便的。
so that's pretty convenient.
我相信这会使页面的两个拷贝，
And my belief is that enough to make both copies of the page,
页面的两个映射都是只读的。
so both mappings of the page read only.
所以，希望现在我们可以得到写入错误。
So hopefully now we'll start getting write faults.
是否可以清除 PTE_W 位，
Is it possible to do to clear the PTE_W bit,
在 flags = PTE_FLAGS(*pte) 之前，
before you say flags equals PTE_FLAGS of pte,
这样原来的 flags 才是正确的。
and that way like the original flags is just the correct thing.
哦，我明白了，把东西放在这里。
Oh I see, you put away up here.
是的。
Yeah.
好的，我会试一下，
Yeah, I'll get that shot,
似乎正常工作了，那就说得通了。
seems to work, that makes sense.
好了，我现在得到了写入错误，
Okay, so now I get my write fault,
正是我们所希望的，
which is what we're hoping for
这个写入错误意味着
and hopefully what this write fault means is
其他进程试图修改这个页面，
that one of the other processes tried to modify the page
而 RISC-V 对此产生了页面错误。
and the RISC-V generated a page fault from that.
我们要[]它，
And, we're gonna want to [] to that
通过复制这个页面，并映射为读写。
by making a copy of the page and mapping it read write.
在我们这样做之前，
Before we do that,
为了确保我们所看到的，
just to make sure that what we're seeing,
你知道这里的 f ，这个 scause ，
you know this, this, this f here, this scause,
让我想到，
that is sort of making imagine that
我们希望是保存错误，
we're seeing what we want to see namely a store fault,
让我们看看实际发生了什么。
let's actually go look and see where that happened.
我们知道这是进程 id 是 3 ，
We know it's process id 3,
进程 id 1 是 init ，
process id 1 is init,
进程 id 2 是 shell ，
process id 2 is the shell
所以进程 id 3 可能是 cowtest 。
and so maybe process id 3 is going to be cowtest.
我们可以看看 cowtest.asm 。
We can look in, we can look in cowtest.asm.
看看 9da ，
And look for 9da
它是否是一个可以生成保存页面错误的指令。
and see if it makes sense, as a instruction that could generate a store page fault.
糟糕，看起来不太好。
Oops, don't look so good.
我不记得 auipc 是做什么的，
I can't remember what auipc does,
但我不相信它有保存的操作。
but I don't believe it performs a store.
有人想到，发生了什么事吗？
Any guesses what's going on?
如果看到的页面错误有意义，那就太好了。
It'd be nice, if the page fault who are seeing actually make sense.
我告诉你，这个页面错误发生在 shell 中，
I'll tell you, it turns out this page fault occurred in the shell
在 shell fork 之后， exec cowtest 之前，
after the shell fork, but before it exec cowtest
所以，我们查看的是错误的 asm 文件，
and so we're really looking at the wrong asm file,
正确的 asm 文件是 shell.asm 文件，
turns out the right asm file is shell.asm file,
我们去那里找 9da 。
we'll look for 9da there.
是的，在 shell 中， 9da 是一条存储指令，
Yes, and in the shell 9da is a store instruction
它位于这个 parsecmd 函数的开头，
and it's at the beginning of this parsecmd function,
它解析我们输入的 cowtest 命令，
that actually parses the cowtest command that we typed
并如何处理它，也就是 exec ，
and figures out what to do with it, namely call exec,
就像保存到堆栈一样，
as doing a store into the stack,
它是前言，保存被调用者保存寄存器。
it's the preamble that stores the callee saved registers.
这不令人惊讶，
And not surprisingly that,
这应该是我们收到的第一个页面错误，
this should be the first page fault we get,
因为它在堆栈上，
because it's on the stack,
函数在 fork 之后做的第一件事返回是
you know the very first thing those functions do after fork returns is
它们修改在堆栈中的变量，
they modify their variables in the stack
然后砰的一声，不出所料，这导致了保存页面错误。
and boom, unsurprisingly that causes a store page fault.
关于为什么得到错误，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about why we're faulting?
我有一个简短的问题，
I have a quick question,
你怎么知道是在 shell 中而不是 cowtest ？
how did you figure out it was in the shell rather than in cowtest?
因为我在 cowtest 里面看到 9da ，
Because I looked at 9da in cowtest
而那个不是保存指令。
and that is not a store instruction.
我想，天哪，这是怎么回事。
I thought gosh what could possibly be going on.
现在，看看进程 id 。
Now, look at process id.
那么 pid 3 是 shell ，还是。
Three, so is pid 3 to shell or is it.
pid 3 是， pid 2 是打印提示符的 shell ，
Pid 3 is, pid 2 is the shell that printed that prompt,
pid 3 它创建的下一个进程，
pid 3 is the next process that's created
所以最初 shell fork 得到 pid 3 。
and so initially the shell forks to make pid 3.
但 fork 之后，它仍在运行 shell ，
But after the fork, it's still running the shell,
它是 shell 的子进程运行着 shell ，
it's a child of the shell running a copy of the shell,
它将调用 exec 来运行 cowtest ，
it's going to call exec to run cowtest,
但它还没有做，
but it hasn't done it yet,
它没有到达那里，
it hasn't been able to get that far,
因为当它写入堆栈时，得到一个保存页面错误。
with taking a store page fault, when it writes to stack.
那么，您能澄清一下，
So, can you clarify,
这是否意味着进程 id 为 2 的 shell 存在错误，
does that mean that there's an error with the shell related process id 2,
因为它没有正确的数据让子进程拥有正确的数据，
because it doesn't have the proper data in order for the child to have the right data
或者是进程 id 为 3 的错误。
or is it a error with process id 3.
这是一个页面错误，发生在进程 id 3 中。
It's a page fault, that occurs in process id 3.
是的，但是我们看到的 bug 就像。
Right, but the bug that we're seeing right here like.
这是在实现写入时复制 fork ，
This is implementing copy-on-write fork
我们刚才在 vm.c 中所做的是
and what we just did in vm.c was
写保护父进程和子进程中的每一页。
write protect every single page in the parent and the child, right.
这是这行正在做的事情，
That's what this line is doing,
所以，下次父进程或子进程在用户代码有保存时，
so the next time either the parent or the child has a store from user code,
它将保存到写保护页中，
it's going to be a store into a write protected page,
因为每一页都是写保护的，
because every page is write protected,
所以它会导致页面错误。
and so it will cause a page fault.
哦，这就是我们想要的页面错误。
Oh, so this is the proper page fault that we want.
对，我只是在检查那个，
This, right and I was just all I was doing was checking that,
所发生的事情正是我们认为的，
that what's going on is exactly what we think is going on,
而不是其他的 bug 。
as opposed to some other bug.
好的。
Okay alright.
所以我们在这里得到一个保存页面错误，
So we took a page fault here in this store
是 shell 在 fork 之后的第一个保存。
which is presumably the first store the shell does after the fork.
好的，所以现在我们要处理这些，
Okay, so now we have to handle these,
现在你要在这个页面错误中做一些有用的事情。
now you want to do something useful in this page fault.
所以， trap.c 和用户错误中的页面错误处理程序。
So, where's the page fault handlers in trap.c and user fault.
我想我们在哪里插入代码无关紧要。
I think it pretty much doesn't matter where we insert code to.
我是说，这里有很多不同的 uservec 的情况，
I mean, there's all these different cases here that uservec,
uservec 或 usertrap ，
this uservec or usertrap,
usertrap 就是添加另一个 usertrap ，
the usertrap is dealing with just going to throw in another else,
我们只对写入错误感兴趣，
we only interested in write faults,
我们很高兴读这些共享页面，
we're happy to read these shared pages,
因为所有的东西都在那里，只是写[]，
because all that is there, it's just write to on [],
所以。
so.
现在，我相信你知道，
Now, it turns out as, I'm sure you know,
我们将需要使用代码，
that we're going to need to use the code,
我要在两个不同的地方写代码，
I'm about to write from two different places,
我要把它封装在代码中，
I'm going to just wrap it up in the code,
让页面的复制在一个函数中，我称为 cowfault 。
that makes the copy of this page in a function, I'm gonna call cowfault.
它需要知道当前的页表，
It needs to know the current page table
也需要知道我们在 stval 上出错的虚拟地址。
and it needs to know the virtual address that we faulted on stval.
有时它可能会因为内存不足而失败，
Sometimes it can fail, because say it runs out of memory,
可能 kalloc 会失败，
maybe kall- kalloc will fail,
所以我们需要为返回值做好准备。
so we need to prepare for return value.
不管失败的原因是什么，
And pretty much no matter what the failure is,
我们都会杀死这个进程，
we're gonna kill this process, right,
如果我们没有杀死它，
if we didn't kill it,
如果出现失败，我们让 cowfault 返回 -1 ，
we'll have cowfault return -1, if there's a failure,
如果没有失败，则返回 0 。
returns 0, if there's no failure.
如果没有失败，
There's no failure,
我们将依赖于 cowfault 使虚拟地址可写，
then we're going to rely on cowfault having made this virtual address writable,
所以当 usertrap 返回时，
so that when usertrap returns,
这个进程可以继续成功。
the process can actually continue successfully.
为什么这么放，
Why that you put,
有没有理由
like is there a reason
为什么把这一行放在 else if devintr 之上。
why you put this line above the else if which dev- devintr.
我不这样认为,
I don't think so,
它是否正确，取决于 devintr 做了什么，
whether it's correct depends on what devintr does,
查看一下，
just take a look,
风险是 devintr 可能会，
the risk is that devintr might,
因为某种原因看到设备中断，
see a device interrupt for some reason,
即使我们出现了页面错误。
even though we are on a page fault.
所以我们只要看看 devintr ，
So we just gotta check that devintr,
看一下 scause 是 f ，
looks at scause, and scause is f,
它将返回 0 。
it's going to return 0.
所以，我只想确定如果。
So, just want to make sure that if.
是的，如果 devintr 返回 0 ，
Yeah, if devintr returns 0,
那么它将继续执行我们的代码，那很好。
then it's gonna go on to our code, that's fine.
好的。
Okay.
好的，现在我们只需要写。
Okay, now we only need to write.
实际上，有一件事我想在这里提醒，
Actually this one thing I want to observe here
如果出现失败，我们就会杀死这个进程。
and that's that if there's a failure, we kill the process.
所以，这很不幸，
So, this is unfortunate,
那就太棒了，
it would be fantastic,
大多数情况下，
if instead you know most of the time,
进程通过调用系统调用来分配内存或其他什么，
processes allocate memory or whatever by calling system calls,
系统调用可以返回一些错误值 -1 或其他，
the system calls can return some error value -1 or something,
如果出现失败，进程就可以做一些适当的事情，
if there's a failure and the process can then do something appropriate,
它知道如何处理这一失败，
if it knows how in order to deal with that failure,
但是这里，因为没有系统调用，
here though because there's no system call,
没有任何明显的方式来告诉进程出了问题，
there's not any obvious way to tell the process that something went wrong,
这是令人恼火的，
which is irritating,
你可以想象解决这个问题的方法，
you can imagine solutions to this,
例如在一些更复杂的操作系统中，
for example in some more sophisticated operating system,
我们可以有比如 alarm 的用户故障处理程序，
we could have something like the alarm user fault handler that you implemented,
我们可以调用，
that we could call up into
表示我们不能继续你的进程了，
to say look you know we can't continue your process,
因为我们无法修复这个页面错误，
because we can't fix this page fault,
但我们想告诉你出了问题。
but we want to tell you something went wrong.
但我们现在不会这么做，
But we're not gonna do that now,
杀死这个进程要简单得多。
it's much simpler to just kill the process.
好的，所以我们要实现这个 cowfault 程序，
Okay, so we have to implement page, this cowfault program,
使用一个对应当前页表的 pagetable ，
takes a, on a pagetable to current this page table,
这个参数，出现错误的虚拟地址。
this argument, the virtual address that the fault occurred on.
好的，所以我们要考虑的第一个问题，
Okay, so the first question we have to worry about,
什么时候处理用户程序产生的虚拟地址，
when dealing with virtual addresses that the user program produced,
就像这个地址一样，
like this one,
如果它是一个完全疯狂的地址，
is what if it's a completely crazy address,
比如在进程[顶部]上方，
like way up above the top of the process,
如果地址在 trapframe 或 trampoine 页面上，
what if it's an address like in the trapframe or in the trampoline page,
或者在堆栈保护页上。
or in the page, the stack guard page.
所以有人可以想出一种方法，
So can anybody sort of outline a strategy
保护自己不受用户进程故意在疯狂地址上出错的影响。
for defending ourselves against the user process intentionally faulting on crazy addresses.
是不是有个最大虚拟地址。
Isn't there like a max virtual address.
是的，确实会出现，
Yes, yes there is and that will actually come up,
但是用户地址空间的顶部在 MAXVA 下面，
but the top of the user address space is below MAXVA,
而且堆栈保护页面，
and the like the stack guard page,
我们不应该允许，
which we shouldn't be allowing, right,
不应该把它当作写入时复制的东西。
shouldn't be treating as a copy-on-write thing.
好的，我会在这里展示一个解决方案。
Alright, I will, I'll show a solution here.
我们在这里调用 walk 。
We're just gonna call walk for now.
有一件事可能会出错的是，
And one thing that can go wrong is
walk 找不到页表条目，
walk doesn't find a page table entry,
所以，对于进程可能引用的大多数非法页面，
so for most illegal pages that a process might refer to,
没有 pte ，
theres no pte,
而且只有几个例外，
and there's only a few exceptions to that,
所以如果我们检测到非法，
so if we detect the illegal,
如果我们检测到 pte 没有找到，
if we detect detect the pte not found,
从 walk 返回 -1 ，
return value from walk and return -1,
我们几乎处理了所有的情况，
we've handled almost every case,
唯一的情况是 walk 会在哪里返回页表条目，
the only cases I'm aware of, where walk would return a page table entry,
但是我们不想允许对其进行写入，
but we don't want to allow writes to it
是 trampoline tramframe 和堆栈保护页面，
are for the trampoline trapframe and stack guard pages,
这些都没有 PTE_U 。
and those all have PTE_U clear.
所以我要检测非法地址的方法是
So the way I'm going to detect crazy addresses illegal addresses is
通过检查 PTE_U 是否被设置，
by checking that PTE_U is set,
另外，只要检查一下 PTE_V ，
and also, just checks look at PTE_V,
如果其中任何一个没有设置，
and if either of those is clear,
那我们就知道这是个不好的地址，
then we know this is like not an okay address,
只需返回 -1 ，杀死进程，
and just return -1, so killed process,
所以我相信处理了所有的非法地址，
so I believe taking care of all the, illegal addresses,
用户进程可以使用的。
the user process could use, try to use.
好的，我们怎么才能知道，
Alright, how can we find out,
我们想要一份拷贝，
we want to do a copy,
现在我们想要这个进程页面的复制，
now we want to make this process copy of the page,
我们怎样才能找到要复制的页面。
how do we find the page to copy from.
这里我有个问题。
I have a question here.
请说。
Please.
使用 PTE_U 来判断页面是否，
Wouldn't the strategy of using the PTE_U to judge if the pages,
如果是合法的写入时复制页面，
if they're, if it's a legit page for copy-on-write,
这个策略是不是对长期进程不友好，
wouldn't this strategy not be very good for the long-term process,
也许你会地址空间中添加一些其他部分，
maybe you add some other part to the address space,
它可能是可写的，
which is which is supposed to be a writable,
它们应该是只是可读的，
which are only supposed to be readable,
但这在这里没有考虑到，
but that doesn't get taken care of here,
你还得再回来一次。
as in you'll have to come back here again.
你说得对，
You're absolutely right,
如果我们要添加任何其他有趣的分页功能，
if we are to add any other interesting paging feature,
比如懒分页，
like maybe lazy page allocation, for example,
我们必须重新审视这些决定，
we have to revisit these decisions
然后想出一些其他的策略来决定，
and come up with some other strategy for deciding
这是不是写入时复制页面，
is this a copy-on-write page,
这是不是一个懒分配页面，
is this a lazy allocation page,
这是不是一个调出到磁盘的页面，
is this a page-out to disk pages,
比如内存映射文件。
to say memory map file.
我们需要更复杂的，
And we need more sophisticated,
最终我认为，
you know, in the end I think,
大多数正式的操作系统都保留了自己的数据结构，
and most serious operating systems actually keep their own data structure,
不是一个页表，
nothing to do with, you know not a page table,
而是某种程度上模仿页表，
but sort of mimicking a page table,
它描述了进程的地址空间，
that describes the process's address space
并在描述了每个页面的含义，
and sort of describes what each page means
以及它的状态是什么，
and what its state is
我们必须参考那张表。
and we have to consult that table.
但是对这个实验来说，
But for this lab,
因为我们没有其他功能，
since we don't have those other features
我们不确定它们会是什么样子，
and we're not sure what they would be,
我只想做些简单的事，
I'm just gonna do something straightforward
事实上，我们不得不回来修复它，
and indeed we would have to come back and fix it,
如果我们把 xv6 做得更复杂。
if we made xv6 more sophisticated.
如果 va 大于 MAXVA ，不会产生 panic 吗，
And wouldn't that panic if va is more than MAXVA,
因为 walk 。
because of the walk.
[]，会的。
[] me, you would.
看看这个，也许是这个过程。
Now, look at that, maybe it's the process.
是的，我想你是对的。
Yeah, I think you're right.
太糟糕了。
That's too bad.
好的，你说得对，
Okay, so we're certainly, you're right,
好的，在这件事上我错了。
alright, well I was wrong about this.
等等，如果你检查 MAXVA ，能直接返回 -1 吗？
Wait, can you just return a -1, if you just check the MAXVA.
我认为观察到的情况是，
I think the observation is
如果用户试图编写程序写入非常大的地址，
that if the user tries to intentionally program tries to write to very large address,
当然，你不能避免这个，
of course, you can't expect to survive that,
但是在这里是用一个非常大的地址调用 walk ，
but what we would do here is call walk with a very large address
看看这里， walk 的实现，
and looking at here, the implementation of walk in the,
它会产生一个 panic 。
and it's going to panic.
然后我们就可以使用相同的方法 walk 地址，
Then we can just use the same approaches walk address,
我也有同样的 bug ，
does I had this same bug,
你可以像其他人说的那样返回 -1 ，
you can just return -1 like other people are saying,
如果在 walk 之前 va 大于 MAXVA 。
if va is greater than MAXVA before walk.
让我失望的是，测试似乎没有测试这一点。
What I'm upset about is that the tests don't seem to test this.
因为我没有把这个放进我的解决方案里。
Because I didn't put this in my solution.
好的。
Okay.
好的，那么我们怎么才能找到，
Okay, so how do we find,
我们想要复制页面，
that we need, we want to copy the page,
如何获得指向页面的指针，
how do I get a pointer to the page
指向我可以复制的页面的指针。
to the pointer to something I can copy.
PTE2PA 。
The PTE2PA.
是的，所以，它在 pte ，
Yeah, so, it's just in the pte,
我要复制到哪里，
where am I gonna copy to,
我应该复制到什么地方。
what should I copy to.
一个几乎被分配的页面。
A nearly allocated page.
是的，所以我调用 kalloc ，
Yeah, so I just called kalloc,
当然， kalloc 可能会失败，
of course kalloc is likely to fail,
所以我会捕获它，
so I'm gonna catch that,
我们要看看这个，
we're actually gonna see this,
所以我放一个 print 语句，这样我们就知道了。
so I'm gonna put a print statement, so we know.
好的，我们。
Okay, we.
那不是 pa2 吗，那个等于。
Is that pa2, that equal.
嘿，我留了这个错误，
Hey, I actually made this error
我想重现它，
and I wanted to reproduce it,
这样我们才能追踪到它，
so that we would have to track it down,
对我来说，你太聪明了。
but you're too clever for me.
我要从 pa1 复制到 pa2 。
I want to copy two pa2 from pa1.
好的，那么我该怎么，我需要做些什么，
Okay, so how can I, what do I need to do
为了映射新的页面 pa2 进入地址空间。
in order to map this page, this new page pa2 into the address space.
我应该输入什么？
What should I type?
有两种方法，
There's like two broad ways,
可以使用已存在的取消映射和映射，
there's either unmapping and then mapping with the built-in that exist,
或者你可以操纵这些位。
or you could manipulate the bits.
是的，我太懒了，
Yeah I am way too lazy
不想解决如何使用 munmap 和 mmap ，
to figure out how to use munmap and mmap,
所以我在这里创造一个新的页表条目。
so I'm gonna just cook up a new page table entry right here.
我有个问题，
I have a question,
实际上我几乎在每个实验都遇到了这个问题，
so actually I ran into this issue in almost every lab
因为某种原因，我需要重新映射，
in which I somehow needed to re-map things
因为它经常发生，
and because it occurred too often,
我实现了一个可以重新映射，
I implemented a map that which could re-map basically,
我想知道这是不是一个糟糕的设计，
and I was wondering is that a bad design choices,
比如危险，所以。
like dangerous, so.
不，这完全合理，
No, no, that's totally reasonable,
xv6 中的函数是，
you know the functions in xv6 are,
专门针对现有的 xv6 ，
are you know specialized to xv6 as it exists,
它们假设其他代码是如何工作的，
and so they you know they make assumptions about how the other code works,
它们产生 panic ，
they have panics in them,
捕获以意外方式使用它们的代码，
that are intended to catch other code using them in unexpected ways,
但是如果你改变了 xv6 的工作方式，
but if you change the way xv6 works
你需要做不同的事情，
and you need to do different things,
它是完全合理的，
then it's totally reasonable
你需要能够在重新映射时没有 panic ，
to modify you know you need to be able to re-map this without a panic,
旧的 xv6 不需要这样做。
well, old xv6 never needs to do that.
如果你的代码这样做了，
If your code does so,
你可以随意修改所需的任何内容。
you should feel free to modify anything you need to.
好的，所以，方法就在这里，
Okay, so okay, so the deal is here,
我们有一个写保护的页面，
we had a write protected page
可能与另一个进程共享，
that was probably shared with another process,
在这里，我们必须对另一个进程做些什么，
what do we have to do to that other process at this point,
我们需要对另一个进程做些什么。
what do we need to do to the other process.
我们可以什么都不做，
We can just not do anything,
然后当出现页面错误时，
and then when it page faults,
我们分配一个新页面并删除原始页面。
we allocate a new page and remove the original one.
完全正确，
That's absolutely right,
所以你可以想象做一件事，
so you could imagine doing something,
但是要正确地做它是相当复杂的，
but it would be quite complex to do it correctly
所以我们什么都不做，
and so we just do nothing,
如果另一个进程从来没有写入这一页，
and if the other process never write this page,
那么就不是问题，
well it's not a problem,
如果它写了这一页，
if it does write a page,
那么它就会经历这一切，
then it will go through all this,
它会复制一份，也会安全地进行，
it will make a copy and it'll proceed safely as well,
所以什么都不做，是完全合理的。
so doing nothing is totally reasonable.
好的，现在我们将返回，
Okay, so now we're going to return,
返回值是 0 ，因为没有错误，
the return value of 0, since there was no error
希望这个过程会。
and hopefully the process will.
也许我们应该释放物理页面，
Maybe we should should free the physical page right,
或者我们还没有到那一步。
or are we not there yet.
我们没有。
We are not.
我想我们要单步了，我们不应该，是的。
I guess we're going steps, we shouldn't, yeah.
如果我这么做了，会发生什么。
So if I did this, what would happen.
它们肯定会崩溃，是的。
Well they would definitely crash, right, alright.
所以我们不要这样做，
So let's not do this
或者我不知道我们会不会崩溃，
or I don't know if we'll crash,
但是我们，
but we would then be,
如果我们释放页面，
if we if we free the page,
它肯定是 pa1 ，
it would be presumably pa1,
因为我们不会释放 pa2 ，
because we don't have free pa2,
因为我们用的是 pa2 ，
because we're using pa2,
如果我们释放 pa1 ，这意味着另一个进程会有问题，
if we free pa1, that means the other process has got a problem,
它现在已经映射到地址空间，
it has now mapped into its address space
大概是使用执行指令，我不知道是什么，
and presumably using executing instructions in, I don't know what,
我们刚刚释放的页面，
a page that we just freed
可能会被重新用于其他目的，
and might be reusing for some other purpose,
写些别的东西，
writing something else over,
所以我不愿意释放它，尽管它是。
so I'm reluctant to free it, although it's.
是的，很遗憾，出现很多事情，
Oh yeah, so sadly, among many other things,
在原始的 xv6 中， walk 不会从 vm.c 以外调用，
xv6 walk is never called from outside of the vm.c, in ordinary xv6,
但是现在我们正在做。
but now we're doing it.
好了，我们到哪儿了。
Alright, where were we.
好的，记得我们得到的第一个页面是 scause 2 ，
Okay, remeber the very first page what we got was scause 2,
为什么我们会得到 scause 2 页面错误。
why are we getting scause 2 page faults.
这是非法指令，
It's an illegal instruction,
这是下一个问题，
like this is the next problem,
我们现在必须解决这个问题。
we have to solve this problem now.
出了什么问题，
What's gone wrong,
或者猜一下可能出了什么问题？
or what are what are some plausible guesses for what might have gone wrong.
所以当我输入 cowtest ，
So the sequence we when I type cowtest,
我们认为发生的情况是 shell fork 是写入时复制 fork 。
what we think happens is that the shell fork is copy-on-write fork.
我们有个子进程在运行 shell 指令，
We have a child running the shell's instructions,
可能接受保存错误，
probably taking store faults,
但是为了处理这些保存错误，
but for handling those store faults correctly
然后子进程执行，
and then the child execs,
子进程复制 shell 执行 cowtest 。
the child copy the shell execs cowtest.
这可能会对父进程 shell 造成什么坏事。
What bad thing might that do to the parent shell.
当你调用 exec 的时候，
Well, when you call exec,
exec 的实现冻结了所有进程的当前页面，
the implementation of exec freeze up all the process's current pages,
然后分配新页面将文件加载到你的 exec 中。
and then allocates new pages to load the file into your exec.
子进程会发生什么，
What's going to happen in the child,
子进程 shell 调用 exec ，
the child shell calls exec,
它冻结了所有的页面，
it freeze all of its pages,
这会对父进程 shell 造成什么影响。
what's that gonna do to the parent shell.
会不会。
Is it gonna end up.
哦，对不起。
Oh sorry.
它会不会意外地释放 shell 的页面。
Is it going to accidentally free the shell's page pages.
是的，我们会释放 shell 的每一个页面，
Yes, we're gonna free every single one of shell's pages,
除了一两个要写入的页面。
except the one or two that the that were written.
所以这包括了 shell 指令页面，
So this includes the shells instruction pages,
然后我们要重新分配它们，
and then we're going to reallocate them,
它们会立即被 exec 重新分配，用来存放其他东西，
they're going to be instantly reallocated by exec to hold other stuff,
从我们运行的 cowtest 文件中加载，
loaded from the file that we're running cowtest,
所以这会彻底改变 shell 的任何东西，
so that's going to totally change everything in the shell underfoot
不出所料，它会立即崩溃。
and unsurprisingly, it's going to instantly crash.
所以，我们没有以某种方式释放这些页面，
So, we have not free those pages somehow,
它们看不到这个。
they don't see that.
我有一个简短的问题，
A quick question,
这里的 sepc 指向哪里，
what does the sepc here point to
你能从哪个汇编文件中找到那个指令吗？
which assembly file would you find that instruction?
好。
Well.
你说它是 shell ，它是。
You said its shell, right, it's the.
上次是因为其他错误，
Last time was for some other fault,
在那里它是 shell ，
somewhere else it would shell,
这里，我不知道是什么，
what it is here I actually don't know,
我从来没有，
I never,
我没有花时间去追查这件事。
I did not unfortunately take the time to track this down.
所以这个问题可能有多个答案，
The, so one problem with any answer,
即使我能给你答案，
even if I could give you an answer,
所以答案是 shell 或者 cowtest ，
so the answer is either the shell or cowtest,
对于进程 id 3 ，也可能是 cowtest 。
for process id 3, that again is the, it's probably cowtest.
我只是说我不完全知道这是怎么回事，
I just say I don't completely know what's going on here,
查看 asm 文件可能没有帮助，
looking at the asm file is unlikely to be helpful,
因为我们认为已经发生的整个问题是，
because the whole problem that we believe has happened is that,
保存指令的页面被释放并重新使用，
the page holding instructions was freed and reused,
所以，它们不再执行 asm 文件中的指令，
and so they were therefore not executing the instructions in the asm file anymore,
或者执行一些垃圾，
or executing some garbage,
所以我们可以看看地址 1004 ，但是它，
so we could look at address 1004 but it,
它不会真正告诉我们发生了什么。
it wouldn't really tell us what had happened.
我们可能使用调试器找出这一点，
We might we probably could find this out using the debugger,
我们可以在 gdb 中打断，然后查看指令，
we could break in gdb and then look at the instructions,
它实际上是一个 1004 指向的虚拟地址。
it's actually at whatever virtual address 1004 points to.
更进一步的问题，关于那个[]，
Quick follow-up question, about that [],
所以我的理解是我们得到了一个非法指令错误，
so my understanding is that we're getting an invalid instruction fault,
因为我们改变了指令页指令物理内存，
because like we're changing the instruction page instruction physical memory underfoot,
那些内存被写了别的东西，
and like the memories just being written to something else,
有没有可能，比如某些幸运的情况下，
is it possible that, like in some lucky case,
它们正在被重写，
that they are being rewritten,
但是当我们再次查看它时，
but when we look at it again,
它正在被重写为有效的指令页，
it's being rewritten to valid instruction pages,
所以我们开始执行随机指令，
so we actually to start executing like random instructions
却没有得到非法指令错误，
and we don't actually get an invalid instruction fault,
我们得到一些其他错误。
we get some other fault.
是的，绝对的。
Yes, absolutely, absolutely.
是的，我是说什么事都有可能发生。
Yeah, yeah I mean really we're now, like anything could happen.
我明白了。
I see.
我猜不到，
I would not have been able to guess,
如果我没有做这个实验，
if I had not done this lab,
在这里，我猜不出会出什么问题。
I wouldn't be able to guess what will go wrong at this point.
事实上，我认为我在这一点上还看到了其他奇怪的事情发生。
Indeed I think I've seen other strange things happen at this point.
可能是第一页数据有垃圾，
It's maybe the data, may be the first page that has garbage
它里面有数据，
and it actually has data
并且 shell 会遍历完整的垃圾数据，
and shell trips over some complete garbage data,
比如堆栈，而不是指令。
like stack, instead of instructions.
好的，所以我们不想马上释放页面，
Okay, so we don't want to free the page right away,
我们只想在页面真的不再使用的时候释放它。
we, we only want to free the page when it's really not being used anymore.
那么有没有人能提出标准，
So can anybody propose criterion
何时应该或不应该释放每个页面的内存？
for when we should or shouldn't free the page for each page of memory?
我们可以记录有多少次，
We could keep track of like how many times are
就像在 kalloc 中，无论你什么时候，
like basically whenever in kalloc whenever you,
你应该递增和递减某些类型变量，
you should increment and decrement some type variable
并保持所有不同地址的数组。
and keep an array of like all the different addresses.
是的，没错。
Yes, yeah exactly.
所以，考虑这个问题的一种方式是，
So, one way to think about this is
我们只想在页面引用为零的情况下，释放该页面，
that we want to only free a page, when there's zero page tables that refer to it,
但是，可能会有很多，
but there could be many,
如果一个程序 fork 再 fork ，
if a program forks and forks again forks again,
我们现在可以有三到四个不同的进程，
boy, we can now have like three or four different processes,
都引用写入时复制 fork 到这一页，
that all refer to copy-on-write fork to this one page,
所以这个计数，
so that this, you know this count of
有多少页表引用一个页面，
how many times how many page tables refer to a page
因为 fork 继续增长，
and go up due to fork
当进程退出时，可以下降，
and they can go back down when a process exits
或者调用 exec ，它会清除所有页表条目的引用，它会将所有这些引用从页表条目中清除，
or calls exec you know it clears all these references out of its page table entry
或者如果进程进行写入并导致写入错误，
or if a process actually does a write and causes a write fault,
这也是我们减少一个引用的情况，
that's also a situation in which we have one fewer reference,
减少一个到页面的页表引用。
fewer page tables referring to a page.
所以我们需要一个计数，
So we want to keep a count,
我们想要通过计算引用页面的页表条目来进行计数。
and we want to count by counting the number of page table entries that refer to a page.
所以我们需要考虑如何保持这个计数，
So we need to think about how to maintain this count,
什么时候增加它，
and when to increment it,
在代码中的什么位置递增和递减。
exactly where in the code to increment it and decrement it.
好的，所以它们，
Okay so they,
如果，你可能意识到，
if there's as you maybe aware,
有多种方法可以维持这一计数，
there's multiple ways to maintain this count,
我的方法是创建一个名为 refcount 的数组，
the way I do it is I make an array called refcount,
给每一页一个计数。
just gonna have it for every page a count.
我们需要知道有多少条目在 refcount 中，
We need to know how many entries are in refcount,
在 xv6 中，很简单，
in xv6, so simple,
它只使用固定数量的物理内存，
that it just has it just uses a fixed amount of memory, physical memory,
我们只需要对每页物理内存一个计数，
we only need to keep a count per page of physical memory,
我们知道，根据对 kinit 的观察，
we know that, from inspecting kinit,
xv6 仅使用 PHYSTOP ，物理内存量，
that xv6 uses only PHYSTOP, amount of physical memory,
我们只需要保持每页的计数，而不是每字节，
we only need to keep a count per page, not per byte,
所以我们要把 PHYSTOP 除以 4096 ，
so we're going to divide PHYSTOP by 4096,
这就是我们需要的数组元素。
that's how many array elements we need.
在更正式的操作系统中，
In a more serious operating system,
我们不知道有多少内存可用，
we don't know how much memory is available,
除非我们检查硬件，
until we inspect the hardware,
我们不得不动态分配这个数组。
we might have to, we would have to allocate this array dynamically.
有什么问题吗，把计数放在哪里？
Any questions about, where to put the counts?
好的。
Alright.
事实上。
Actually.
是。
Yes.
我在想，你直接使用 4096 是什么原因，
I'm wondering is there a reason that you're using 4096 specifically
而不是页面大小的宏。
and not the page size macro.
是的，原因是我记得 4096 ，
Yeah the reason is that I can remember 4096
我不记得页面大小宏的名称了，
and I don't remember the name of the page size macro,
不过，如果你愿意的话，我很乐意用。
but I'm happy to use it, if you like.
实际上，如果 xv6 的目的是可移植的，
It actually if if xv6 was intended to be portable
并且能够在具有不同页面大小的各种不同的机器上运行，
and to be able to run on all kinds of different machines with different page sizes,
我们必须对此更加小心，
we have to be much more careful about this,
但是有 500 种方式使得 xv6 完全不能移植。
but there's 500 ways in which xv6 is totally not portable.
所以，我不担心这件事。
So, I don't worry about it.
我猜页面大小是由硬件决定的，在哪里。
Page sizes determined in hardware and I guess where.
在硬件中，RISC-V 手册上说，页面是多大。
In the hardware, that RISC-V manual says, how big a pages.
是的，因为，
Yeah, because the,
是 MMU 接受虚拟地址，
it's the MMU that takes a virtual address
并使用它来索引页表。
and uses it to index into the page table.
哦，对，因为地址转换是在硬件中进行的，
Oh, right right, because the address translation happens in hardware,
所以硬件必须知道页面大小，好的。
so the hardware has to know how big pages are, okay.
它是可配置的，
It's configurable,
但是有几种不同的策略可以告诉硬件使用，
but you know there's a couple different strategies you can tell the hardware to use,
但是我们告诉它使用 4096 字节的页面。
but we tell it to use 4096 byte pages.
好的。
Okay.
抱歉，教授，
Where, sorry professor,
哪里，我想这是个 C 的问题，
so where are, I guess is a C question,
所以我们的全局变量比如 refcount 存储在哪里，
so in where our global variables like refcount stored,
比如它们与特定的处理器绑定吗？
like what, like are they associated with specific processor?
这是内核，
This is the kernel,
所发生的是可执行文件，
what's going on is that the file, the executable file,
编译器和加载器或链接器产生的，
that the compiler and the loader or linker produces,
有这种，
has this sort of this,
表明有多少数据，
indicates how much data,
程序中所有全局变量的总大小是多少。
how the total size of all the global variables in the program.
我们看不到这些代码，
And, so we don't see the code for this,
但是当 QEMU 加载内核时，
but when QEMU loads the kernel,
实际上是这样的，
well what's really going on is
当你编译的时候，
when you compile,
程序调用链接器，计算基于，
the program call the linker figures out based on,
查看所有全局变量及其大小，
look at all the global variables and their sizes
并在内存中分配一个地址，
and assigns an address in memory,
是的，分配给每个全局变量。
yeah, to each global variable.
这就是它在内存中的地方。
And that's where it lives in memory.
我是说，我们只是安排，
I mean, and, we just arrange that the you know,
所以 xv6 内核使用 10000 字节各种全局变量，
so xv6 kernel uses you know 10,000 bytes of various global variables,
并且在引导过程将其加载到存储器中的任何地方，
and wherever the boot process loads it into memory,
比如在地址一百万处，
say at address a million,
它就使用这些地址用于全局变量。
it just uses those addresses for the global variables.
我明白了，
I see,
这是不是跟这个类似，
is this, is this similar to how,
就像在磁盘上只有一份程序的指令的副本，
like there's only one copy of like the instructions for a program on disk
这个程序只有一份全局变量的副本。
and there's only like one copy of a kind of global variables for that program on this.
好的，一个程序，
Well, a program this,
好的，我不知道该怎么回答，
well, I'm not really sure how to answer this,
我的意思是，当你声明一个全局变量时，比如 int x ，
I mean the the, when you declare a global variable, like int x,
当你编译时，编译编译器和链接器决定
when you compile, the compiler and the linker just decide
基于谁知道它是什么或者它是可配置的，
based on who knows what or it's configurable,
但是它们决定了变量的地址，
but they decide the address for that variable,
它们决定 x 地址定为 1000 ，
they decide alright boy x is going to address 1000,
然后代码读取或写入 x ，
and then the code that reads or write x,
如果我们有代码 refcount[0] 等于 1 ，
you know if we have code that says refcount of zero equals one,
但是编译只是把内存设置在 1000 地址，
you know, but that compiled into was just setting the memory at address a thousand
或者链接器决定把 refcount 放在哪里，
or wherever we linker decided to put refcount
进行存储，设置存储器地址 1001 。
which is does a store to set the memory address 1001.
是的，它不是，
Yeah, it's not,
它实际上是类似的事情，
it's actually almost exactly the same thing
和你运行普通用户程序时发生的。
that happens when you run an ordinary user program.
链接器和编译器决定内存全局变量的位置。
You know the linker and compiler decide where memory global variables are.
它们就在那里，而且可以工作。
They just being right there and, and it just works.
我很抱歉，这不是一个很好的解释。
I'm sorry, that's not much of an explanation.
好的，只需定义此全局计数数组，每个物理页一个，
Alright, so just a define this global array of counts one per physical page
我们需要在不同的地方修改这些计数，
and we need to modify these counts in various places,
当然，当我们第一次分配页面时，
certainly when we first allocate a page,
我们会说它有一个引用，
we're going to say that it has one reference,
因为我们把页面地址给调用 kalloc 的程序，
because we return the address of the page to whoever called kalloc
这时，只有该程序引用了这个页面，
and at the moment only that program has a reference to this page,
因此，我将此页面的引用计数设置为 1 。
so I'm just gonna set the refcount for this page to be 1.
所以，首先我要计算一下页码，
So first of all I'm just going to calculate the page number,
它是页面的地址除以 4096 ，即页码。
which is the address of the page divided by 4096, the page number.
然后我将设置
And then I'm going to set
刚分配的页面的引用计数为 1 。
the reference count for the page we just allocated to 1.
有关于这些代码的问题吗？
Any questions about this code?
因为我知道引用计数会有 bug ，
Just because I know that I'm going to have bugs with reference counting,
我在这里做了一些合理性检查，
I'm actually do a little bit of a sanity check here
只是，引用计数应该是 0 ，
and just, the you know the reference count really should be zero,
如果我们刚刚分配的页面是释放的，
if the pages we just allocated a page was free,
最好它的引用计数为 0 。
boy it better have a reference count of zero.
对这个代码，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this code?
好的，通常我们希望增加引用计数
Alright, so in general we want to increment the reference count
我们增加，
when we add,
当写入时复制 fork 添加指向现有页的页表条目时，
when copy-on-write fork adds a page table entry that points to an existing page
我们想要，
and we want to,
实际上，我们想要减少引用计数，
actually, we want to decrement the reference count,
事实证明，在很多地方，
as it turns out in many places,
例如，当进程退出时，
for example when a process exits,
我们需要递减其所有页的引用计数，
we need to decrement the reference count of all its pages,
当你调用 exec 时，
when you call exec,
它释放所有当前内存，
and that frees all the current memory,
因为它会取代它，
because it's going to replace it,
我们想要减少所有的引用计数，
we want to decrement all those reference counts,
当发生写入时复制页面错误时，
when a copy-on-write page fault happens
然后我们复制了一份，
and we make a copy,
我们想要减少旧页面上的引用计数，
we want to decrement reference count on the old page,
这些位置都是可以同时释放页面的，
it turns out these are all the same places that concurrently free a page,
因为当前的 xv6 ，
because the current xv6,
考虑每个页面只有一个引用，
think there's only ever one reference to each page,
所以在大多数我们想要减少的地方，
so in most of the places we care about where we want to decrement,
并发调用 kfree ，
there's concurrently a call kfree,
所以我要做的是
so what I'm gonna do is
修改 kfree 使其具有稍微不同的语义，
modify kfree to be have somewhat different semantics
使 kfree 成为，
and to have kfree be,
某种可以减少引用计数的函数，
sort of a function that decrements the reference count
并且仅当引用计数降至零时才释放页面。
and free the page only if the reference count has dropped to zero.
我的意思是，我会修复所有调用 kfree 的地方。
I mean, I'll just automatically fix all the places that call kfree.
好的，我们需要检查，
Alright so, we need to actually do the check,
在我们用垃圾数据填满页面之前。
before we fill the page with junk.
所以，这让事情变得有点复杂，
So, this makes a little bit more complicated,
因为即使在 kfree 中已经有一个锁的临界区，
because even though there's a critical section with locks in kfree already,
我们也不能使用它，
we can't use it,
因为它发生在我们将页面填满垃圾数据之后。
because it happens after the point at which we filled the page with garbage.
所以，我们需要一个锁，
So, we need a lock,
因为我们可能释放同一页面，
because we could be free
在同一时间从多个不同的内核，
in the same page at the same time from multiple different cores,
同样，我要找到页码，
again I'm gonna find the page number
通过将物理地址除以 4096 。
by dividing the physical address by 4096.
我想再一次 panic ，只是一次合理性检查，
I want to panic, again, just a sanity check,
如果我们要释放一页的话，
gosh, you know if we're freeing a page,
最好有超过零的引用计数。
that better have more than zero refcounts.
如果页面有多个引用计数，我们需要返回。
We need to return if the page has more than one reference count to it.
实际上，让我们减少引用计数，
Actually, let's decrement the reference count,
我们想在解锁后返回，
we want to return after we release locks
我们必须记住一个变量，
and we have to remember a variable,
我将记住该页面是否有更多引用，
I'm gonna remember whether the page has more references
然后释放锁，然后返回，
and then release locks and then return,
所以我将创建一个临时变量，
so I'm gonna make a temporary variable
该变量包含，然后释放，
which has the and release,
如果还有引用这个页面的话，
then say if there's still references this page,
我们就返回，不要释放它。
let's just return and not free it.
只有当引用计数降到零时，我们才释放它。
And only if the reference count drop to zero, we free it.
有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
你能不能再解释一下，
Can you explain again,
为什么要在这个过程中取得 kmem->lock ？
why you have to acquire the kmem lock this process?
为什么整段都要获取它？
Why have to acquire it all?
是的，当你在做页码计算的时候。
Yeah when you're doing the page number calculations and.
是这一行，
It's this line,
这一行和下一行是问题的关键，
really is this line, the next line of the problem,
问题是，在这个页面上，
the issue is that on this page,
我们现在可能有多个对它的引用，
we now is likely has more than one reference to it
如果两个进程有相同的引用，
and so if two processes with a reference to the same
有指向相同页面的页表条目，
with the page table entry point at the same page,
如果它们同时在不同的核心上退出，
if they both exit at the same time on different cores,
它们会同时对相同的页面调用 kfree 。
they're both gonna call kfree for the same page at the same time.
你可以为引用计数变量创建一个新的锁，
Could you just create a new lock for the reference count variable
然后使用它吗？
and use that as well?
是的。
Yes.
是的，基本上，
Yeah, basically everybody,
所有操纵这些计数的代码
you know all code that manipulates these counts
都需要使用相同的锁，
need to use the same lock,
但我觉得锁是什么并不重要。
but I don't think it matters what lock is.
好的，这就解决了大部分我们关心的减少的问题，
Okay, so this takes care of decre-, most of the decrement we care about,
每一次释放页面，
every time the page is free,
我们只有在引用计数为零的情况下才释放。
we're really gonna you know only free if the reference counts fails to zero.
我们也需要增加引用计数，
We also need to increment the reference count,
我们需要在哪里增加引用计数。
where do we need to increment the reference count.
好的，因为我知道我们需要做好这件事，
Well, because I know we're going to need to do it right,
任何人都可以调用的函数。
the function that anybody can call.
再一次，如果有什么不正常，我想引起 panic ，
Again I want to panic if something is weird,
所以如果地址很奇怪，
so if the address is wacky,
我当然不想超出数组的末尾。
I'm certainly don't want to go beyond the end of the array.
或者如果我们不想增加页面的引用计数，
Or if we don't want to increment the reference count of page,
引用计数为零，
reference counts currently zero,
这也是一个错误，
that's also an error,
我只是把这些放在这里，
I'm just putting these in there,
因为从我的代码经验中知道，
because I know from experience with my code
正是那种地方，我会有 bug 。
that this is exactly the kind of place, I'm going to have a bug in.
好的，我应该从哪里调用增加。
All right, where should I call increment from.
你有 uvmcopy ，当你。
You have uvmcopy when you.
我认为 uvmcopy 是唯一另一个引用页面的地方。
I think uvmcopy is the only place that makes another reference to a page.
好的，我这么做了，
Alright gosh, I'm going with this well,
这几乎无关紧要。
it almost doesn't really matter.
我们创造了另一个对 pa 的引用，
We're making another reference to pa,
所以我想使用 incref(pa) 。
so I want to say incref(pa).
很可能会遇到来自编译器的问题，
Or, likely to run into trouble from the compiler,
如果我们不把它的定义放在 traps.h 中。
if we don't put a definition for it in traps.h whatever.
好的,
Okay,
让我们看看。
let's see.
那太快了，
That was pretty quick,
那是 kfree ref ，
that was kfree ref,
kfree 不高兴。
kfree is unhappy.
好的，这是在引导过程的早期，
Okay, well here's the time we don't know, is very early in the boot process
也许是出了什么问题的一个线索。
which is maybe a hint it to what's going wrong.
如果有人有任何猜测，我很乐意听听，
If anybody has any guesses, I'd be happy to hear them,
同时，启动调试器，尝试获取回溯信息。
meanwhile just fire up the debugger try to get backtrace.
这是在 kinit 中，
It is during kinit,
因为你正在尝试将内容放入链表，
because you're trying to put things into the linked list
但是链表尚未分配。
and you haven't allocated yet.
所以，当你尝试将所有内容加载到链表中时，
So you in when you trying to load everything into a linked list,
在那之前你没有调用 kalloc 。
you haven't called kalloc before that.
是的，完全正确，
Yeah that's exactly right,
所以，请看这里的操作，
so, see that in action here,
好的，我得到 panic ，
okay I got the panic,
输入 where ，它在，
type where and it's in,
这里是 kfree 被调用，并引起 panic ，
here's kfree being called and paniced
它一开始就是从 freerange 调用的，
and it's being called from freerange right at the beginning,
当我们在初始化空闲列表时，
when we're initializing the free list indeed,
所以在 freerange 有一些需要修复的东西，
so there's something to be fixed in freerange,
问题是我调用 kfree ，
the problem is I'm calling kfree,
如你所说，我调用 kfree ，
as, as you said I'm calling kfree,
但是当然，所有的引用计数都是零，
but of course, all the reference counts are zero
当参考计数为 0 时， kfree 会出现 panic ，
and kfree panics at the reference count of zero,
所以我把这个改为。
so I'll just, I'll just hack this to be.
这个怎么样。
How about that.
好的，我们现在可以启动了，
Oh okay, we managed to boot now,
干得不错，
by wonderful done,
让我们看看。
let's see.
好的，让我们再运行一次 cowtest 。
Okay, so let's run the cowtest again.
嗯，我们通过了这个 simple 测试，
Um, we pass this simple test,
我们通过了 simple 测试，这很棒。
aha, so we passed the simple test, which is great.
我们通过了一次 three 测试，
And we passed one time through the three test,
但是我们没有通过，
but we didn't pass,
我们没有通过第二次 three 测试，
we didn't make it through the second time to the three test
test 测试触发了我添加到 trap 的打印语句，
and the three test triggered the print statement that I added to trap
输出 cow kalloc failed ，
which said cow kalloc failed,
只有在我们内存不足的情况下才会打印出来。
which only would print it if we're out of memory.
所以我们内存不足了。
So we're out of memory.
为什么我们内存不足了。
Why are we out of memory.
所以我们每次分配的时候都会更新引用计数，
So we've updated reference counts every time we've allocated,
但是当我们释放的时候，没有减少计数。
but we haven't called decrement counts, whenever we've tried to free right.
那么我应该在哪里加上。
So where should I add the.
嗯，按照你目前的方法，
Well, with your current approach,
我认为 pa1 的引用计数需要减少，
I think pa1 that reference count needs to get decrement,
所以我们需要 kfree 它。
so we would need to kfree it.
是的，就是这样。
Yeah exactly.
我想可能是有人在 45 分钟前提出了这个问题，
So, I think somebody actually possibly brought this up, 45 minutes ago,
让我们看看，
let's see,
让我们释放 pa1 ，而不是 pa2 。
let's free pa1, not pa2.
好的，现在 kfree 的意思是，
Okay, and so now what kfree means,
不是释放这个页面，
now is don't is not free this page,
kfree 的意思是减少这个页面上的引用计数，
it's what kfree means is decrement the refcount on this page
如果是零的话，才释放它，
and free if it's zero
以此类推，在只有一个 fork 的简单情况下，
and so forth in a simple situation, where there was just one fork
所以有两个对页面的引用，
and so there were two references to the page,
我们在复制中得到了写入错误，
and we've taken a write fault to make a copy,
现在 kfree 要做的就是将计数减为 1 ，
where now all kfree is going to do is decrement the count to be one
现在另一个进程可以使用这个页面，
and now the other process can use the page,
我们并不是要释放它。
we're not actually gonna free it.
好的，希望现在，
Okay so hopefully now,
我们不会在 cowtest 中内存不足。
we'll, not run out of memory in the cowtest.
嗯，我喜欢它，
Um, I love it,
好的，我们通过了 three 测试，
okay, we made it through the three test,
没有内存不足。
without running out of memory.
好的，
Alright,
遗憾的是，我们还没有完成，
we're not done, sadly,
我们在 file 测试中有一个有趣的错误，
we have this interesting error in the file test,
那么让我们来看一下 file 测试。
so let's take a look at the file test.
好的，这是 filetest ，
Alright, so here's the filetest
它在测试的注释中说，
and it says right in the comments of the test,
它测试 copyout ，
that it's investigating copyout,
所以，是很好的线索，我们的问题在哪里，
so, good hint of where our problem is going to be,
实际上失败的事情是，
the thing that actually failed is,
我的意思是你必须稍微发挥你的想象力，
I mean you have to use your imagination a little bit,
但是，错误信息似乎是这个，
but, the error message seems to be this one,
同时从两个不同的进程打印。
printed from two different processes at the same time.
事实上，这个测试是一个循环，
And indeed, this is a loop, this test is a loop,
四次迭代，就是 fork ，
that for four iterations, just forks
因此它将产生四个并发进程，
and so it's going to produce four concurrent processes,
这个错误消息将被交错，
this error message will be interleaved,
所以我们需要知道读取失败的原因，
so we need to know why that read failed,
如果我们想了解 bug 是什么，
if we want to understand what the bug is,
我们需要知道读取失败的原因。
we need to know why the read failed.
第一步可能是找出读取返回了什么，
The first step is maybe to figure out what the read actually returned,
我们所知道的是，
all we know is that,
它返回了除了 sizeof(i) 之外的其他东西，
it returned something other than sizeof i,
但是我们不知道它返回了什么，
but we don't know what it returns,
所以我要捕获返回值，
so I'm going to capture the return value,
我要打印返回值。
and I'm going to print the return value, at least know.
哦，我有个问题，抱歉，
Oh, I have a question, sorry,
看起来有三个线程失败了，
it seems like three of the threads failed,
但是，其中一个并没有结束，
but, one of them didn't end,
它还在运行，
it's like still running,
为什么它没有失败？
why is it not failing?
为什么第三个线程没有失败？
Why did the third thread not fail?
第四个，如果你做 cowtest 然后 echo ，
The fourth if you, if you do cowtest and then echo,
另一个还会继续运行，
that other one is still going to be running
你会看到更多的输出。
and you're gonna see more output.
是的，三个失败了，一个没有。
Yes, three failed and one didn't.
嗯，让我们先调查一下为什么它们中的任何一个都失败了，
Um, let's just finish investigating why any of them failed,
然后我可以猜一猜，
and then I can make a guess
虽然不知道为什么其中一个没有失败。
although I don't really know why one of them didn't fail.
好的，这里发生的情况是， read 返回的是 -1 。
Okay, so, what's happening here is that read returning -1.
那么为什么 read 返回的是 -1 。
So why is read returning -1.
你可能会假设，
You might hypothesize
我们将这个 buf 传递给 read ，
that the you know we were passing this buffer into read,
你可能会想象，
you might imagine that the,
你知道 read 需要做一些事情，
you know read, and read needs to do something
也就是调用 copyout 将文件数据复制到这个缓冲区中，
namely called copyout to copy file data into this into this buffer,
我们传递给 read 的，
that we passed to read,
也许它出了什么问题，
maybe something's going wrong with that
它与写入是复制 fork 的关系。
and its relationship to copy-on-write fork.
那么让我们来看看 read ，
So let's take a look at read,
看看它为什么会失败。
and see why it's failing.
找出，为什么 read ，
Track down, why read,
好的，那么让我们来捕捉，
alright, so let's capture the,
read 所有 sys_read 调用 fileread ，
read all sys_read does this calls calls fileread
在获取一组参数之后。
after fetching a bunch of arguments.
所以我们修复这个，
So we'll fix this to,
走进一步，来理解什么东西出错了。
take one step closer to understanding why things are going wrong.
我们希望 cc 会为 -1 。
We are expecting cc to be -1.
嗯，有意思，
Um, that's interesting,
我们没有看到 cc 等于 -1 。
we never saw cc minus equals -1.
事实上，失败发生了，
In fact, the failure occurred,
失败从这里开始发生，
a failure starts occurring here,
在我们得到任何相应的 cc 打印语句之前，
before we get any corresponding cc print statements
它根本不是 -1 ，
and it's not -1 at all,
而是 4 ，这是一个非失败值。
it's four, which is a non failure value.
所以这意味着，
So what that means is,
在调用 fileread 之前的一些事情，
that something before the call the fileread
一定触发了这次返回，
must have caused must have triggered this return,
这里的其中一个函数，
so one of these functions here,
导致 read 返回 -1 。
has caused read to return -1.
请随意猜猜，在我输入时。
Please feel free to guess while I'm typing.
顺便说一下，这对我来说完全是个意外，
This was a complete surprise to me by the way,
当我追踪到它的时候。
when I tracked it down.
哦，我想这个文件是描述符。
Oh, I think the file is descriptor.
是的，文件描述符，我看到了，
Yeah, the file descriptor, I saw,
我所期望的是 fileread 失败是由于某些原因，
what I expected was that fileread was failing due to something
而且 copyout 对写入时复制的页面做不正确的事情，
and copyout not doing the right thing with copy-on-write pages,
但这不是失败的地方。
but that is not at all where the failure is.
好的，如果我们想找出，
Okay, so, if we want to find out,
它是 argfd 或者 argint 或者 argaddr 失败，
like it's either argfd or argint or argaddr, that's failing,
让我们从 argfd 开始，
let's start with argfd,
我要把打印语句放在这里，
I'm just gonna stick print statements in here,
帮助我找出，
to help me figure out,
这些失败情况中的哪一个触发了，
which one of these failure cases actually triggering triggering,
有两个地方返回的是 -1 ，
so like two places it returns -1,
这个是 fd 本身出了问题，
this one there's something wrong with the fd itself,
所以我们在 argfd 返回 -1 的地方添加打印语句。
so we're gonna get these print statements on cases where argfd returns -1.
是的，这是什么意思， fd 。
Yeah, what is this mean, fd.
好的，我们希望这些 fd 打印输出，发生在错误之前，
Alright, so the that we expect these fd printouts to occur, just before the error,
所以我们看到的是 fd 9 ，
so we saw is fd 9,
它是 fd 9 ，这会导致错误，
it was fd 9, this causes the error,
所以 fd 9 没有通过这三个测试中的一个，
so fd 9 failed one of these three tests,
但我们知道它不小于零，
but we know it's not less than zero,
我碰巧知道它不大于等于 NOFILE ，即打开的文件数，
I happen to know it's not greater than equal to NOFILE, a number of open files,
这意味着 ofile 数组 9 ，
and so that means that the ofile array for 9,
文件描述符 9 必须为 0 ，
file descriptor 9 must have been 0,
也就是说，在这个进程中，没有文件描述符 9 。
that is in this process, there is no file descriptor 9.
所以不知道什么原因，写入时复制测试，
So somehow, copy-on-write test,
这个代码和写入时复制测试传递了无效文件描述符来读取。
this code and copy-on-write test is passing an invalid file descriptor to read.
所以，文件描述符来自 fds ，
So, file descriptor in comes from fds,
fds 来自对管道的调用。
fds comes from a call to pipe.
怎么会，
How could I,
通常 pipe 如果没有失败，
usually pipe, if it doesn't fail,
它会将文件描述符留在数组中，
it leaves the file descriptor in the array,
那么这怎么会出错呢。
so how could this go wrong.
哦，我们都知道答案一定是什么什么 copyout 。
Oh, we all know the answer has to be blah blah blah copyout.
那么缺失的部分是什么。
So what's the missing piece.
我是说，我想有一件事能帮我找到这件事，
I mean, I guess like one thing that help me track this down
因为我意识到首先 fd 不应该是 9 ，
as I realized at least first of all fd should not be 9,
在每一次迭代中， 9 都是你所期望的值，
on every iteration 9 is kind of the value that you would expect,
在上一次迭代的基础上增加一些，
kind of add on the last iteration,
这像是对管道的最高调用。
that's kind of like the highest call to pipe.
是的，它们都会得到 9 ，你说得对。
Yeah yeah, they all got 9, you're right.
有什么东西使内存变得奇怪。
There's something they're kind of touching each other's memory strange.
是的，完全正确。
Yeah, that's exactly right.
所以， fds 管道，
So, you know the fds pipe,
管道转换文件描述符的方式是它调用 copyout ，
the way pipe turns the file descriptors is that it calls copyout,
将分配的文件描述符号复制到调用方的地址空间。
to copy the file descriptor number that is allocated into the caller's address space.
我们这里用的是写入时复制 fork ，
Well, we're using copy-on-write fork here,
所以如果我们不小心，
so if we're not careful,
至少最初只有一个页面，
so at least initially there's just one page
它在所有进程之间共享。
and it's shared among all the processes.
所以第一个调用管道的进程，
So the first process that calls pipe,
如果出现问题，
if something goes wrong,
管道系统调用可能会写入共享页面，
the pipe system call might conceivably write the shared page,
然后该文件描述符的值将被所有进程看到，
and that value that file descriptor will then be seen by all the processes,
而不仅仅是实际分配描述符的进程。
instead of just the process that actually allocated the descriptor.
它们看到这个是一种假设风险。
They really see this as a kind of at least hypothetical risk.
那么让我们来看看，
So let's look at what,
试着想象一下，
try to imagine,
因此，首先让我们看看 sysfile ，
so first let's look sysfile
看看管道是如何复制出分配的文件描述符的，
to see how pipe copies out the file descriptors that allocates
事实上，在这里有两个调用 copyout ，
and indeed down here, these two calls to copyout
复制管道数组中的两个元素，
to copy the two elements of that pipe array,
所以，管道使用 copyout
so pipe is using copyout
将文件描述符复制到用户空间的数组中。
to copy the file descriptor numbers into the array in user space.
那么， copyout 做了什么呢。
So what is copyout do.
嗯，它查找虚拟地址以找到物理地址。
Well, it looks up the virtual address to find a physical address.
然后它会写入复制该物理地址，仅此而已。
And then its writes, copies over that physical address and that's it.
因此，它没有做的一件事是
So, one thing it is not doing is
检查写权限，没有查看 PTE_W 。
checking for write permission, doesn't look at PTE_W.
因此，对于这个页面，
And so with this page,
在这个虚拟地址指向的写入时复制的共享页面，
at this virtual address refers to a copy-on-write shared page,
copyout 根本不知道，它会继续写下去。
copyout just has no idea it just goes ahead and writes it.
所以我的意思是，当管道调用 copyout 时，
So I mean indeed, when pipe calls copyout,
它会写一个共享页面，
it's going to be writing a shared page,
所有 fork 进程都可以看到这个修改，
that all of the forked processes see this modification,
而不仅仅是调用管道的进程。
not just the process that called pipe.
对于为什么会发生这个，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about, why this is happening?
好的。
Okay.
好的，你们都知道我们需要修改 copyout ，
Alright, so as you all know we need to modify copyout to
由于 copyout 是查找虚拟地址并将其转换为物理地址，
since copyout is looking up a virtual address and translating into a physical address,
但是它没有使用 MMU ，
but it is not using the MMU,
所以 MMU 没有捕捉到写入错误，
so the MMU doesn't catch the write fault,
因为 MMU 没有参与，
because the MMU is not involved,
walkaddr 查看页表本身
walkaddr looks at the page table itself
而不是让 MMU 为它查看页表。
instead of basically getting there MMU to look at the page table for it.
好的，那么，我们需要修改 copyout ，
Okay, so, we need to modify copyout,
我们不想调用 walkaddr ，
we don't wanna call walkaddr,
walkaddr 只产生一个物理地址，
walkaddr just produces a physical address,
我们实际上需要页表条目，
we actually want the page table entry,
因为我们想要查看权限位，
because we want to look at the permission bits,
查看它是否是写入时复制受保护的页面，
to see if it's a copy-on-write protected page,
所以我们将调用 walk 。
so we're going to call walk instead.
我们需要检查所有常见的错误，
We need to check all the usual errors,
所以可能根本就没有映射，
so maybe there's no mapping at all,
也许不是有效的映射，
maybe it's not a valid mapping,
或者可能是用户代码不允许使用的映射，
or maybe it's a mapping that the user code is not allowed to use,
在所有这些情况下，这都是个错误，
in all those cases, it's an error,
但这一次，我们可以返回一个错误，
but this time we can actually return an error,
调用 read 返回 -1 ，而不是终止进程，
actually call read to return -1 instead of killing the process,
那就好了。
that's nice.
接下来，我们需要知道如何检查它是否是写入时复制页面。
Next we need to know how to check whether it's a copy-on-write page.
有没有什么想法可以让我们
Any, any ideas for how we can
检查我们是否应该复制，
check whether we should apply copy
我们是否应该在这一点上进行复制。
whether we should do a copy at this point.
写入时复制页面
What's different about between copy-on-write pages
和普通的非共享页面有什么不同？
and just sort of ordinary unshared pages?
引用的数量会更大吗？
Would the reference count to be large?
嗯，这是很好的观点，
Um, that's a good point,
如果引用计数大于 1 ，
if the reference count was greater than one,
这当然是一个非常好的线索，
that's certainly a very strong hint,
那是一个写入时复制页面。
that's a copy-on-write page.
但是，如果引用计数为 1 ，
But if the reference count is one,
是否意味着它不是写入时复制页面。
does that mean it's not a copy-on-write page.
如果你 fork 了，子进程出现写入时复制错误，
It turns out if you fork and the child takes a copy-on-write fault
做了复制，将引用计数减少到 1 ，
and makes a copy that reduces the reference count to one,
但是该页在父进程中仍然是写保护的。
but the page is still write protected in the parent.
在这种情况下，我们也许可以不受影响地进行修改，
And actually probably we could get away with modifying in that case,
所以我想我们可以检查一下引用数量，
so I think we actually could check the reference count,
并且仅被视为写入时复制页面，
and only treated as a copy-on-write page,
如果引用计数大于零，
if the reference count greater than zero,
但是我要做的是不同的，甚至更容易的捷径，
but what I'm gonna do is different, even easier shortcut
如果页面是写保护的，
and say if the page is write protected,
那么页面可以被写保护的唯一方式，
the only way a page can be write protected
并且设置了 PTE_U 位，
and have the PTE_U bit set,
在这个版本的 xv6 中，它是写入时复制页面。
in this version of xv6 is it's a copy-on-write page.
因此，与检查引用计数相比，这为我节省了一点打字时间，
So this has saved me a little bit of typing compared to checking the reference count,
我们已经在 trap.c 中编写了处理此问题的代码。
we already wrote the code to deal with this in trap.c.
所以我就从这里调用那个代码。
So I'm just gonna call that code from here.
我们仍然需要处理可能的错误返回，
We still have to deal with the possible error return,
如果是个疯狂的地址。
if it's a, a crazy address.
哦，事实上，我们没有。
Oh, actually, we don't.
好的。
Alright.
好的，所以页面不能写入，
Alright, so the pages not write at all,
我们会调用 cowfault ，
we're just going to copy-on-write fault
并且 cowfault 会复制并设置页面可写，
and copy-on-write fault does the copy and it makes the page writable,
所以我想我们在这一点上就快做完了，
so I think we're, we're almost done at this point,
然而，如果 copyin ，
however if copyin,
如果 cowfault 没有产生一个。
if cowfault did make a.
我们删除这个。
We gonna get rid of this.
如果 cowfault 制作了复制，
If cowfault did make a copy,
它将修改页表条目中的物理地址，
it's going to modify the physical address in the page table entry,
因此我们必须再次从页表条目中取出物理地址，
so we have to pull that physical address out of the page table entry again,
防止它被修改，
in case it was changed,
我正要这么做，
I'm just gonna do that,
我们这里有页表条目。
since we have the page table entry right here.
我认为这或多或少已经足够了。
And I think this is more or less enough.
那么，关于 copyout 的修改，有什么问题吗？
So, any any questions about the modification to copyout?
好的，我要做一个 cowfault 的全局声明。
Alright I got to make a global declaration for cowfault.
漂亮。
Ah beautiful.
好的，看起来不错。
Alright, that's looking great.
有没有人知道我们已经完成了。
Anybody happen to know if we're done.
完成或没有，
We may or not be,
我们还必须通过 usertests 。
we also have to pass usertests.
哦，好的，让我删掉这些输出语句。
Oh, alright, let me get rid of this print statements.
我认为 execout 测试故意分配了大量内存。
I think the execout test intentionally allocates a lot of memory.
好的，在我们等待用户测试结果的同时，有任何问题吗？
Alright, any questions, while we wait for the verdict from usertests.
哦， usertests 不开心，
Oh, usertests was unhappy,
我想这是一块熟悉的破损，
I think this is a familiar piece of damage
有人已经提出来了，
which somebody's brought up already,
这是 walk 中的 panic ，
it's, it's the panic at walk
如果用户进程，
if the user process,
usertest 我认为是故意做的。
usertests actually I think does intentionally.
我们看看 usertests 。
We'll take a look at usertests.
这是 copyout 测试，
And it's the copyout test,
甚至在它的评论中说，
and even says in the comment,
它将荒谬的指针传递给系统调用。
it passes ridiculous pointers to system call.
好的，那么我们面临的是 copyout ，
Alright, so what we're faced with is copyout,
我们传入一个荒谬的指针，
we pass in a ridiculous pointer,
使用那个荒谬的指针调用 walk ，
it's simply called walk with that ridiculous pointer
然后 walk panic 了，
and walk panics,
如果你给它一个荒谬的指针。
if you give it a ridiculous pointer.
所以，就像有人提到的，
So, as somebody mentioned,
我们不能用荒谬的指针来调用 walk ，
we need to not call walk with ridiculous pointers,
是什么， MAXVA 还是什么。
what is it, MAXVA or something.
好的。
Alright.
当然，我们完全有权返回错误
Of course, we're totally entitled to return an error
如果用户进程传递这个超出的指针。
if the user process pass this outbound pointer.
好的，我希望现在可以通过。
Alright, I'm just hoping it passes now.
我没有发现任何其他问题。
I'm not aware of any other problems.
好了，有什么问题。
Okay, questions.
我想我的问题更宽泛，
I guess my question is more broad,
当我们用小步走的时候，
like we saw when we were doing that with small steps,
我们在这里得到了随机的其他的 bug ，
we're getting random bugs at this point that others have,
如果我们从头开始做实验，
and if we're doing the lab from scratch,
那么有那么多奇怪的 bug 不会让人迷惑吗，
then wouldn't it be confusing to get all of those weird bugs,
你怎么，
and how would how would you,
你怎么知道是不是你写的东西有 bug ，
how do you know whether it's bug with something you wrote
或者你没有，而是其余部分的 bug 。
or a bug because you didn't write the rest of it.
我想我不能回答你的问题。
I'm afraid I cannot answer your question.
关于 bug 的可悲事实，
The the sad truth about bugs,
特别是对内核页面表做了一些有趣的事情而导致的错误，
particularly bugs caused by doing funny things to page tables inside the kernel,
就是每个 bug 都是不同的。
is that every bug, you know every bug is different.
什么才是追踪漏洞的制胜策略，
And how you know what turns out to be the winning strategy for tracking a bug down,
这完全取决于 bug 的本质。
it just depends totally on the nature of the bug.
通常，
My usual,
我不是，
you know I'm not,
我有一些，
I have some,
我有一些策略，
I have a collection of strategies
有时有用，有时没用，
that are sometimes helpful and sometimes not,
比如我坚信，
like I'm a huge believer,
我将打印语句放入代码中，
I'm putting print statements into the code
以便收集信息或验证假设。
in order to gather information or to verify hypotheses.
我经常会花时间看看代码，
I'll often spend time just looking at the code,
只是为了给自己来点头脑风暴，
just for the purpose of generating sort of brainstorming with myself,
试着生成一些东西，
just try to generate you know things
在这一点上可能出错的东西，
that could possibly be going wrong at this point,
然后将打印语句放到[] panic 或其他地方，
and then put print statements in [] panics or something
试图排除各种猜测问题可能是什么东西。
to try to rule in and rule out various guesses at what the problem might be.
另一种可能是，
Another possibility is that
你做了一些，你的代码起作用了，
you know you've made some you know your code worked
或者没有显示这个错误之类的，
or didn't show this error or something,
你知道半小时前你做了一些改变，
you know half an hour ago and you made some changes,
现在你有了一些 bug ，
and now you have some bug,
另一种可能性是，
another possibility is
你可以返回到没有错误的代码版本，
to if you can, you know back up to a version of the code that didn't have the bug
然后一点一点地添加更改，直到错误出现。
and sort of add your changes bit by bit until the bug shows up.
现在，这些都是，
Now, these are,
我不知道有什么策略总是奏效的，
I don't know any strategy that always works
或者甚至有超过一小部分的时间在工作。
or even works more than a fraction of the time.
但真相是你们在这堂课上学到的东西的一部分，
But the truth is part of what you're learning in this class
在学习操作系统的同时，
as well as learning about operating systems,
你正在获得编写和调试代码的经验。
you know you're getting experience writing and debugging code.
抱歉，没有更多的帮助。
Sorry, not to be more helpful.
还有其他问题吗？
Other questions?
好了，我们快下课了。
Alright, we're at the end of class time.
我很乐意多说几句，
I'm happy to talk more,
但是这节课的正式部分我们已经讲完了。
but we're done with the formal part of this class.
好的，我们星期三见。
Alright and to see you all on Wednesday.
哦，抱歉，我还有另一个问题，
Oh, sorry I actually have another question,
当我们第一次看到写入错误时，
when we were seeing our first write fault,
之后我们也看到了对于 shell 非法指令的错误，
we also saw after that for the shell illegal instruction fault
然后是初始化过程的一些东西，
and then something for the init process,
那是什么。
what was that.
好的，我没有一个想法。
Well, I don't have a theory.
初始化进程，我认为不会与任何东西共享页面。
Init process, I don't think would share pages with anything.
我只是不知道，很抱歉。
I I just don't know, I'm sorry.
我们可以。
We could.
我不得不后退一步，
I would have to back up,
这发生得很早，
this happened very early,
当我做实验的时候，
when I was doing the lab,
我们只需要复制页表，其他什么都不用。
we just had to copy the page table, nothing else.
是的。
Yeah.
我想它是，比如 scause f 对于 shell ，
I think it was, like scause f for the shell
我想可能是 scause c 对于 init 进程。
and I think scause c for the init process, maybe.
好的，让我看看，
Alright, let me let's see,
如果你是对的，让我们来看看，我们可以。
if you really, let's let's we can.
让我们从头开始重建实验，
Let's reconstruct the lab from scratch,
克隆。
clone.
好的，我们刚才讲的这一点，
Okay, this point we've just made,
我刚刚修改了 uvmcopy 。
I just made a change to uvmcopy right.
所以我们在这里不能做什么，
So we were, what are we not doing here,
我们没有分配，也没有 memmove 。
we're not allocating and we're not doing memmove.
但我们会，
But we are,
我们会把 pa 传给 mappages ，
we're gonna pass pa to mappages
我想在我第一次跑任何东西的时候。
and I think the very first the very first time I ran anything.
我想这就是当时的状态。
I think this was the state of play.
那是在我们做完 flag 之后，所以。
It was after we did the flag, so so.
好的。
Okay.
好的，让我们清楚。
Alright, so let's clear.
看起来不错。
That looks good.
好的，我们有一个 c ，
Alright, we got a c,
让我们看看 c 指令页面错误，
well let's see c instruction page fault,
好的，所以 scause 2 ，
so okay so scause 2,
我们认为一个共享的进程 id 2 ，
you know, as you know we think a shared process id 2,
你说得对，是进程 id 1 。
man you're right, it's process id 1.
我没有一个想法来解释为什么进程 id 1。
I just don't have a theory for why process id 1.
为什么失控了。
Why it's out of control.
让我们看看它是做什么的。
Let's let's let's look at what it does.
我看看 init 。
I just see init.
好的，它执行这个 shell 。
Okay, it exec this shell.
我不知道。
I don't know.
好的，我有个主意，
You know, okay, oh here's an idea,
进程 id 2 出现错误并退出。
process id 2 is taken a fault and it's exited.
所以你之后做了 fork 。
So you do fork later.
是的，那就是这个等待 init ，
Yeah, so that means that this wait to init,
它返回了，
it has returned, right,
让我们回到循环中，再次调用 fork ，
let's go back around the loop and call fork again
所以，在 fork 之后，
and so you know after fork,
我们现在共享，或者取决于所有这些损坏代码。
we're now sharing or you know depending on all this damage code.
哦，好的，我明白了。
Oh, okay, I see.
哦，是的，那是非常令人困惑的。
Oh, yeah, that's that's very confusing.
哦，是的，这些错误完全是[]，
Oh, yeah, these errors are just like complete [],
因为我们违反了各种直觉，
because we violated all sorts of intuitions
关于事情是如何运作的。
about how things should work.
好的。
Okay.